I want to tell you about the future of money.
[AI] 我想告诉你钱的未来。
Let's start with a story about this culture
[AI] 让我们从一个关于这种文化的故事开始
that lived in Micronesia in the early 1900s. called the Yap.
[AI] 20世纪初生活在密克罗尼西亚的人。叫了一声“呀”。
Now. I want to tell you about the Yap
[AI] 现在我想告诉你关于雅普的事
because their form of money is really interesting.
[AI] 因为他们的货币形式真的很有趣。
They use these limestone discs called Rai stones.
[AI] 他们使用这些石灰石圆盘称为Rai石头。
Now. the Yap don't actually move these Rai stones around
[AI] 现在Yap实际上并没有移动这些Rai石头
or exchange them the way we do with our coins.
[AI] 或者像我们用硬币那样交换。
because Rai stones can get to be pretty massive.
[AI] 因为Rai石头可以变得相当大。
The largest is about four tons and 12 feet across.
[AI] 最大的约4吨12英尺宽。
So the Yap just keep track of who owns part of what stone.
[AI] 所以Yap只需跟踪谁拥有部分what stone。
There's a story about these sailors
[AI] 有一个关于这些水手的故事
that were transporting a stone across the ocean
[AI] 他们正在把一块石头运过海洋
when they ran into some trouble and the stone actually fell in.
[AI] 当他们遇到麻烦时，石头掉了进去。
The sailors got back to the main island
[AI] 水手们回到了主岛
and they told everyone what had happened.
[AI] 他们告诉大家发生了什么事。
And everyone decided that. actually. yes.
[AI] 每个人都决定了。事实上对
the sailors had the stone and -- why not? -- it still counted.
[AI] 水手们有石头，为什么不呢它仍然很重要。
Even though it was at the bottom of the ocean.
[AI] 即使它在海底。
it was still part of the Yap economy.
[AI] 它仍然是雅普经济的一部分。
You might think that this was just a small culture
[AI] 你可能会认为这只是一种小文化
a hundred years ago.
[AI] 一百年前。
But things like this happen in the Western world as well.
[AI] 但类似的事情也发生在西方世界。
and the Yap actually still use a form of these stones.
[AI] 雅普人实际上仍然使用这种石头的一种形式。
In 1932. the Bank of France asked the United States
[AI] 1932年。法国银行问美国
to convert their holdings from dollars into gold.
[AI] 将他们持有的美元转换成黄金。
But it was too inconvenient to think about actually shipping
[AI] 但考虑到实际的运输太不方便了
all of that gold over to Europe.
[AI] 所有的黄金都转移到了欧洲。
So instead.
[AI] 所以相反。
someone went to where that gold was being stored
[AI] 有人去了储存黄金的地方
and they just labeled it as belonging to France now.
[AI] 他们现在把它贴上了属于法国的标签。
And everyone agreed that France owned the gold.
[AI] 所有人都同意黄金归法国所有。
It's just like those Rai stones.
[AI] 就像那些石头一样。
The point I want to make with these two examples
[AI] 我想用这两个例子来说明这一点
is that there's nothing inherently valuable
[AI] 没有什么内在的价值
about a dollar or a stone or a coin.
[AI] 大约一美元、一块石头或一枚硬币。
The only reason these things have any value
[AI] 这些东西有价值的唯一原因
is because we've all decided they should.
[AI] 是因为我们都决定他们应该这么做。
And because we've decided that.
[AI] 因为我们已经决定了。
they do.
[AI] 是的。
Money is about the exchanges and the transactions
[AI] 金钱是关于交换和交易的
that we have with each other.
[AI] 我们彼此拥有的。
Money isn't anything objective.
[AI] 金钱不是任何客观的东西。
It's about a collective story that we tell each other about value.
[AI] 这是一个关于价值的集体故事。
A collective fiction.
[AI] 集体小说。
And that's a really powerful concept.
[AI] 这是一个非常强大的概念。
In the past two decades.
[AI] 在过去的二十年里。
we've begun to use digital money.
[AI] 我们已经开始使用数字货币。
So I get paid via direct deposit.
[AI] 所以我通过直接存款获得报酬。
I pay my rent via bank transfer.
[AI] 我通过银行转账支付租金。
I pay my taxes online.
[AI] 我在网上交税。
And every month. a small amount of money is deducted from my paycheck
[AI] 每个月。从我的薪水中扣除了一小笔钱
and invested in mutual funds in my retirement account.
[AI] 在我的退休账户上投资共同基金。
All of these interactions
[AI] 所有这些相互作用
are literally just changing 1's and 0's on computers.
[AI] 实际上只是在计算机上更改1和0。
There's not even anything physical. like a stone or a coin.
[AI] 甚至没有任何物理的东西。像石头或硬币一样。
Digital money makes it so that I can pay someone around the world
[AI] 数字货币使我可以支付世界各地的人
in seconds.
[AI] 几秒钟之内。
Now when this works. it's because
[AI] 现在，当这起作用的时候。因为
there are large institutions underwriting every 1 or 0 that changes on a computer.
[AI] 有一些大型机构在计算机上每改变1或0就承保一次。
And when it doesn't.
[AI] 而当它没有。
it's often the fault of those large institutions.
[AI] 这往往是那些大机构的错。
Or at least. it's up to them to fix the problem.
[AI] 或者至少。由他们来解决这个问题。
And a lot of times. they don't.
[AI] 很多时候。他们没有。
There's a lot of friction in the system.
[AI] 系统中有很多摩擦。
How long did it take the US credit card companies
[AI] 美国信用卡公司花了多长时间
to implement chip and pin?
[AI] 实现芯片和引脚？
Half my credit cards still don't work in Europe.
[AI] 我一半的信用卡在欧洲仍然不能使用。
That's friction.
[AI] 那是摩擦。
Transferring money across borders and across currencies is really expensive:
[AI] 跨国界、跨货币转账的成本非常高：
friction.
[AI] 摩擦
An entrepreneur in India can set up an online business in minutes.
[AI] 印度的企业家可以在几分钟内建立一个在线企业。
but it's hard for her to get loans and to get paid:
[AI] 但她很难获得贷款和报酬：
friction.
[AI] 摩擦
Our access to digital money and our ability to freely transact
[AI] 我们获得数字货币和自由交易的能力
is being held captive by these gatekeepers.
[AI] 被这些看门人俘虏了。
And there's a lot of impediments in the system slowing things down.
[AI] 系统中有很多阻碍，使事情变得缓慢。
That's because digital money isn't really mine.
[AI] 那是因为数字货币不是我的。
it's entries in databases that belong to my bank.
[AI] 是属于我的银行的数据库条目。
my credit card company or my investment firm.
[AI] 我的信用卡公司或投资公司。
And these companies have the right to say "no."
[AI] 这些公司有权说“不”
If I'm a PayPal merchant
[AI] 如果我是贝宝商人
and PayPal wrongly flags me for fraud.
[AI] 贝宝错误地将我标记为欺诈。
that's it.
[AI] 就这样。
My account gets frozen. and I can't get paid.
[AI] 我的账户被冻结了。我也拿不到薪水。
These institutions are standing in the way of innovation.
[AI] 这些机构阻碍了创新。
How many of you use Facebook photos. Google Photos. Instagram?
[AI] 你们中有多少人使用Facebook照片。谷歌照片。Instagram？
My photos are everywhere.
[AI] 我的照片到处都是。
They are on my phone. they're on my laptop.
[AI] 他们在我的电话里。它们在我的笔记本电脑上。
they're on my old phone. they're in Dropbox.
[AI] 他们在我的旧手机上。它们在升降箱里。
They're on all these different websites and services.
[AI] 他们在所有这些不同的网站和服务上。
And most of these services don't work together.
[AI] 而且这些服务中的大多数都不能协同工作。
They don't inter-operate.
[AI] 它们不相互作用。
And as a result.
[AI] 结果呢。
my photo library is a mess.
[AI] 我的照片库乱七八糟。
The same thing happens when institutions control the money supply.
[AI] 当机构控制货币供应时，同样的情况也会发生。
A lot of these services don't inter-operate.
[AI] 这些服务中有很多是互不操作的。
and as a result. this blocks what we can do with payment.
[AI] 结果呢。这阻碍了我们对付款的处理。
And it makes transaction costs go up.
[AI] 这使得交易成本上升。
So far. we've been through two phases of money.
[AI] 目前为止我们已经经历了两个阶段的资金。
In an analog world. we had to deal with these physical objects.
[AI] 在模拟世界中。我们必须处理这些物理对象。
and money moved at a certain speed -- the speed of humans.
[AI] 金钱以一定的速度流动——人类的速度。
In a digital world. money can reach much farther and is much faster.
[AI] 在数字世界里。钱可以走得更远，也更快。
but we're at the mercy of these gatekeeper institutions.
[AI] 但我们却任由这些把关机构摆布。
Money only moves at the speed of banks.
[AI] 货币只会以银行的速度流动。
We're about to enter a new phase of money.
[AI] 我们即将进入一个新的货币阶段。
The future of money is programmable.
[AI] 货币的未来是可规划的。
When we combine software and currency.
[AI] 当我们把软件和货币结合起来的时候。
money becomes more than just a static unit of value.
[AI] 货币不仅仅是一个静态的价值单位。
and we don't have to rely on institutions for security.
[AI] 我们不必依靠机构来保证安全。
In a programmable world.
[AI] 在一个可编程的世界里。
we remove humans and institutions from the loop.
[AI] 我们将人和机构从循环中移除。
And when this happens.
[AI] 当这种情况发生时。
we won't even feel like we're transacting anymore.
[AI] 我们甚至不会觉得我们在交易了。
Money will be directed by software.
[AI] 资金将由软件来引导。
and it will just safely and securely flow.
[AI] 它将安全地流动。
Cryptocurrencies are the first step of this evolution.
[AI] 加密货币是这一演变的第一步。
Cryptocurrencies are digital money that isn't run by any government or bank.
[AI] 加密货币是不由任何政府或银行运营的数字货币。
It's money designed to work in a world without intermediaries.
[AI] 它是为在一个没有中间人的世界里工作而设计的钱。
Bitcoin is the most ubiquitous cryptocurrency.
[AI] 比特币是最普遍的加密货币。
but there are hundreds of them.
[AI] 但是有几百个。
There's Ethereum. Litecoin. Stellar. Dogecoin.
[AI] 那里有以太坊。莱特币。恒星的多哥康。
and those are just a few of the more popular ones.
[AI] 这些只是比较流行的几个。
And these things are real money.
[AI] 这些东西是真的钱。
The sushi restaurant down my street takes Bitcoin.
[AI] 我住的那条街上的寿司店卖比特币。
I have an app on my phone that I can use to buy sashimi.
[AI] 我的手机上有一个可以用来买生鱼片的应用程序。
But it's not just for small transactions.
[AI] 但这不仅仅是针对小额交易。
In March. there was a transaction that moved around 100.000 bitcoins.
[AI] 三月。有一笔交易转移了大约10万比特币。
That's the equivalent of 40 million US dollars.
[AI] 这相当于4000万美元。
Cryptocurrencies are based on a special field of mathematics
[AI] 加密货币基于数学的一个特殊领域
called cryptography.
[AI] 这就是所谓的密码学。
Cryptography is the study of how to secure communication.
[AI] 密码学是研究如何保护通信安全的学科。
and it's about two really important things:
[AI] 这是关于两件非常重要的事情：
masking information so it can be hidden in plain sight.
[AI] 屏蔽信息，使其可以隐藏在普通视线中。
and verifying a piece of information's source.
[AI] 以及验证一条信息的来源。
Cryptography underpins so many of the systems around us.
[AI] 密码学是我们周围许多系统的基础。
And it's so powerful that at times
[AI] 它是如此强大，有时
the US government has actually classified it as a weapon.
[AI] 美国政府实际上已将其列为武器。
During World War II. breaking cryptosystems like Enigma
[AI] 在第二次世界大战期间。破解像谜一样的密码系统
was critical to decoding enemy transmissions
[AI] 对破译敌人的信号至关重要
and turning the tide of the war.
[AI] 扭转战争的潮流。
Today. anyone with a modern web browser is running
[AI] 今天任何拥有现代网络浏览器的人都在运行
a pretty sophisticated cryptosystem.
[AI] 一个相当复杂的密码系统。
It's what we use to secure our interactions on the Internet.
[AI] 这是我们用来保护我们在互联网上互动的东西。
It's what makes it safe for us to type our passwords in
[AI] 这使我们能够安全地输入密码
and to send financial information to websites.
[AI] 以及向网站发送财务信息。
So what the banks used to give us --
[AI] 那么银行过去给我们的是什么--
trustworthy digital money transfer --
[AI] 值得信赖的数字转账--
we can now get with a clever application of cryptography.
[AI] 我们现在可以巧妙地应用密码学了。
And this means that we don't have to rely on the banks anymore
[AI] 这意味着我们不必再依赖银行了
to secure our transactions.
[AI] 确保我们的交易安全。
We can do it ourselves.
[AI] 我们可以自己做。
Bitcoin is based on the very same idea that the Yap used.
[AI] 比特币基于Yap所使用的理念。
this collective global knowledge of transfers.
[AI] 这是关于转让的全球集体知识。
In Bitcoin. I spend by transferring Bitcoin.
[AI] 比特币。我通过转移比特币来消费。
and I get paid when someone transfers Bitcoin to me.
[AI] 当有人把比特币转给我时，我会得到报酬。
Imagine that we had this magic paper.
[AI] 想象一下，我们有一张神奇的纸。
So the way that this paper works is I can give you a sheet of it
[AI] 所以这篇论文的工作方式是我可以给你一张
and if you write something on it.
[AI] 如果你在上面写点什么。
it will magically appear on my piece as well.
[AI] 它也会神奇地出现在我的作品中。
Let's say we just give everyone this paper
[AI] 假设我们给每个人这份文件
and everyone writes down the transfers that they're doing in the Bitcoin system.
[AI] 每个人都记下他们在比特币系统中进行的转账。
All of these transfers get copied around to everyone else's pieces of paper.
[AI] 所有这些转移都会被复制到其他人的纸片上。
And I can look at mine
[AI] 我可以看看我的
and I'll have a list of all of the transfers that are happening in the entire Bitcoin economy.
[AI] 我将列出整个比特币经济中发生的所有转移。
This is actually what's happening with the Bitcoin blockchain.
[AI] 这就是比特币区块链的实际情况。
which is a list of all of the transactions in Bitcoin.
[AI] 这是比特币中所有交易的列表。
Except. it's not done through paper.
[AI] 除了这不是通过纸做的。
It's done through computer code.
[AI] 这是通过计算机代码完成的。
running on thousands of networked computers around the world.
[AI] 在全球数千台联网计算机上运行。
All of these computers are collectively confirming
[AI] 所有这些计算机都在运行
who owns what Bitcoin.
[AI] 谁拥有什么比特币。
So the Bitcoin blockchain is core to how Bitcoin works.
[AI] 因此，比特币区块链是比特币运作方式的核心。
But where do bitcoins actually come from?
[AI] 但比特币究竟从何而来？
Well. the code is designed to create new Bitcoin according to a schedule.
[AI] 好该代码旨在根据时间表创建新的比特币。
And the way that it works is that to get those Bitcoin.
[AI] 它的工作方式是获取比特币。
I have to solve a puzzle -- a random cryptographic puzzle.
[AI] 我必须解决一个难题--一个随机密码难题。
Imagine that we had 15 dice.
[AI] 想象一下我们有15个骰子。
and we were throwing these dice over and over again.
[AI] 我们一次又一次地掷骰子。
Whenever the dice come up all sixes.
[AI] 每当掷骰子的时候都是六。
we say that we win.
[AI] 我们说我们赢了。
This is very close to what these computers are all actually doing.
[AI] 这与这些计算机的实际功能非常接近。
They're trying over and over again to land on the right number.
[AI] 他们一次又一次地试图找到正确的号码。
And when they do.
[AI] 当他们这样做的时候。
we say that they've solved the puzzle.
[AI] 我们说他们已经解决了这个难题。
The computer that solves the puzzle publishes its solution to the rest of the network
[AI] 解决难题的计算机将其解决方案发布到网络的其余部分
and collects its reward: new bitcoins.
[AI] 并收集其奖励：新比特币。
And in the act of solving this puzzle.
[AI] 在解决这个难题的过程中。
these computers are actually helping to secure the Bitcoin blockchain
[AI] 这些计算机实际上有助于保护比特币区块链
and add to the list of transactions.
[AI] 并添加到事务列表中。
There are actually people all over the world running this software.
[AI] 实际上全世界都有人在运行这个软件。
and we call them Bitcoin miners.
[AI] 我们称他们为比特币矿工。
Anyone can become a Bitcoin miner.
[AI] 任何人都可以成为比特币矿商。
You can go download the software right now
[AI] 你现在可以去下载软件了
and run it in your computer and try to collect some bitcoins.
[AI] 然后在你的电脑上运行，试着收集一些比特币。
I can't say that I would recommend it.
[AI] 我不能说我会推荐它。
because right now. the puzzle is so hard and the network is so powerful.
[AI] 因为现在。谜题如此之难，网络如此强大。
that if I tried to mine Bitcoin on my laptop.
[AI] 如果我试着在我的笔记本电脑上挖掘比特币。
I probably wouldn't see any for about two million years.
[AI] 我大概在两百万年内都看不到。
The miners. professional miners. use this special hardware
[AI] 矿工们。职业矿工。使用这种特殊的硬件
that's designed to solve the puzzle really fast.
[AI] 这是为了快速解决难题而设计的。
Now. the Bitcoin network and all of this special hardware.
[AI] 现在比特币网络和所有这些特殊硬件。
there are estimates that the amount of energy it uses
[AI] 据估计，它使用的能源量
is equivalent to that of a small country.
[AI] 相当于一个小国。
So. the first set of cryptocurrencies
[AI] 所以第一套加密货币
are a little bit slow and a little bit cumbersome.
[AI] 有点慢，有点笨重。
But the next generation is going to be so much better  and so much faster.
[AI] 但是下一代将会变得更好更快。
Cryptocurrencies are the first step
[AI] 加密货币是第一步
to a world with a global programmable money.
[AI] 一个拥有全球可编程货币的世界。
And in a world with programmable money.
[AI] 在一个拥有可编程货币的世界里。
I can pay anyone else securely
[AI] 我可以安全地支付任何人
without having to sign up or ask permission.
[AI] 无需注册或请求许可。
or do a conversion or worry about my money getting stuck.
[AI] 或者进行转换或者担心我的钱被卡住。
And I can send money around the world.
[AI] 我可以把钱寄到世界各地。
This is a really amazing thing.
[AI] 这真是一件了不起的事情。
It's the idea of permission-less innovation.
[AI] 这是一种无需许可的创新理念。
The Internet caused an explosion of innovation.
[AI] 互联网引发了创新的爆炸。
because it was built upon an open architecture.
[AI] 因为它是建立在开放式架构之上的。
And just like the Internet changed the way we communicate.
[AI] 就像互联网改变了我们的交流方式一样。
programmable money is going to change the way we pay.
[AI] 可编程货币将改变我们的支付方式。
allocate and decide on value.
[AI] 分配并决定价值。
So what kind of world does programmable money create?
[AI] 那么，可编程货币创造了一个什么样的世界呢？
Imagine a world
[AI] 想象一个世界
where I can rent out my healthcare data to a pharmaceutical company.
[AI] 我可以把我的医疗数据出租给一家制药公司。
They can run large-scale data analysis
[AI] 他们可以进行大规模的数据分析
and provide me with a cryptographic proof
[AI] 给我一个密码证明
that shows they're only using my data in a way that we agreed.
[AI] 这表明他们只是以我们同意的方式使用我的数据。
And they can pay me for what they find out.
[AI] 他们可以为他们发现的东西付钱给我。
Instead of signing up for streaming services
[AI] 而不是注册流媒体服务
and getting a cable bill.
[AI] 还有电报费。
what if my television analyzed my watching habits
[AI] 如果我的电视分析了我的观看习惯呢
and recommended well-priced content that fit within my budget that I would enjoy?
[AI] 并推荐价格合理的内容，适合我的预算，我会喜欢吗？
Imagine an Internet without ads.
[AI] 想象一个没有广告的互联网。
because instead of paying with our attention when we view content.
[AI] 因为当我们看内容的时候，我们没有注意。
we just pay.
[AI] 我们只是付钱。
Interestingly. things like micro-payments
[AI] 有趣的是。比如小额支付
are actually going to change the way security works in our world.
[AI] 实际上将改变我们世界的安全工作方式。
because once we're better able to allocate value.
[AI] 因为一旦我们能够更好地分配价值。
people will use their money and their energies
[AI] 人们将使用他们的金钱和精力
for more constructive things.
[AI] 为了更具建设性的事情。
If it cost a fraction of a cent to send an email.
[AI] 如果发送一封电子邮件只花一小部分钱。
would we still have spam?
[AI] 我们还会有垃圾邮件吗？
We're not at this world yet.
[AI] 我们还没到这个世界。
but it's coming.
[AI] 但是它来了。
Right now. it's like we're in a world that is seeing the first automobile.
[AI] 马上就好像我们身处一个看到第一辆汽车的世界。
The first cryptocurrency. like the first car.
[AI] 第一种加密货币。就像第一辆车。
is slow and hard to understand and hard to use.
[AI] 很慢，很难理解，也很难使用。
Digital money. like the horse and carriage.
[AI] 数字货币。就像马和马车一样。
works pretty well.
[AI] 效果很好。
and the whole world economy is built on it.
[AI] 整个世界的经济都是建立在这个基础上的。
If you were the first person on your block
[AI] 如果你是你所在街区的第一个人
to get a car with an internal combustion engine.
[AI] 买一辆装有内燃机的汽车。
your neighbors would probably think you were crazy:
[AI] 你的邻居可能会认为你疯了：
"Why would you want this large. clunky machine
[AI] “你为什么要这台又大又笨重的机器
that breaks down all the time. that lights on fire.
[AI] 这种情况一直在发生。那灯着火了。
and is still slower than a horse?"
[AI] 还是比马慢？"
But we all know how that story turns out.
[AI] 但我们都知道这个故事的结局。
We're entering a new era of programmable money.
[AI] 我们正在进入一个可编程货币的新时代。
And it's very exciting. but it's also a little bit scary.
[AI] 这非常令人兴奋。但这也有点吓人。
Cryptocurrencies can be used for illegal transactions.
[AI] 加密货币可用于非法交易。
just like cash is used for crime in the world today.
[AI] 就像当今世界现金被用来犯罪一样。
When all of our transactions are online.
[AI] 当我们的所有交易都在线时。
what does that mean for surveillance -- who can see what we do?
[AI] 这对监视意味着什么——谁能看到我们在做什么？
Who's advantaged in this new world and who isn't?
[AI] 在这个新世界里，谁有优势，谁没有优势？
Will I have to start to pay for things that I didn't have to pay for before?
[AI] 我会开始为我以前不需要付钱的东西付钱吗？
Will we all become slaves to algorithms and utility functions?
[AI] 我们都会成为算法和效用函数的奴隶吗？
All new technology comes with trade-offs.
[AI] 所有的新技术都需要权衡。
The Internet brought us a lot of ways to waste time.
[AI] 互联网给我们带来了很多浪费时间的方式。
But it also greatly increased productivity.
[AI] 但这也大大提高了生产率。
Mobile phones are annoying
[AI] 手机很烦人
because they make me feel like I have to stay connected to work all the time.
[AI] 因为他们让我觉得我必须一直和工作保持联系。
But they also help me stay connected to friends and family.
[AI] 但它们也帮助我与朋友和家人保持联系。
The new sharing economy is going to eliminate some jobs.
[AI] 新的共享经济将减少一些工作岗位。
But it's also going to create new. flexible forms of employment.
[AI] 但它也将创造新的。灵活的就业形式。
With programmable money.
[AI] 用可编程的钱。
we decouple the need for large. trusted institutions
[AI] 我们将对大型设备的需求解耦。受信任的机构
from the architecture of the network.
[AI] 从网络的体系结构来看。
And this pushes innovation in money out to the edges. where it belongs.
[AI] 这将资金创新推向了边缘。它属于哪里。
Programmable money democratizes money.
[AI] 可编程货币使货币民主化。
And because of this. things are going to change and unfold
[AI] 正因为如此。事情将会改变和展开
in ways that we can't even predict.
[AI] 以我们甚至无法预测的方式。
Thank you.
[AI] 非常感谢。
(Applause)
[AI] （掌声）